<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Mind→Theory→Math→Code</title>
        <link>https://brittAnderson.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[Seeking a Language for Theoretical Psychology]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://brittAnderson.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Programming, Programming Languages and Cognitive Theorizing</title>
    <link>https://brittAnderson.github.io/posts/2025-06-18-computer-languages.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on June 18, 2025
        
            by Britt Anderson
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Do the programming languages we know influence the cognitive theories
that we conceive? Does our view of programming's role in computational
cognitive science have a negative effect on our advancement?</p>
<p>A few interesting quotes from Edsger W. Dijkstra's ACM Turning Lecture
(1972) <a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>. For some I have a comment, for others there is nothing to
add.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"[Two opinions from the early days]…The one opinion was that a
really competent programmer should be puzzle-minded and very fond of
clever tricks; the other opinion was that programming was nothing more
than optimizing the efficiency of the computational process, in one
direction or the other."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think the latter is the attitude opinion of most programmers in
computational neuroscience.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The sooner we can forget that FORTRAN has ever existed, the better,
for as a vehicle of thought it is no longer adequate: it wastes our
brainpower, is too risky and therefore too expensive to use. FORTRAN’s
tragic fate has been its wide acceptance, mentally chaining thousands
and thousands of programmers to our past mistakes."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Replace FORTRAN with Python for the modern version. Don't miss the
little bit about programming "as a vehicle for thought." That is what
we most miss with our current popular languages.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"… no loop should be written down without providing a proof for
termination …"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Interesting to see him discussing formal methods 50 years ago.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"We must not forget that it is not our business to make programs, it
is our business to design classes of computations that will display a
desired behaviour."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Note the emphasis shift from program to computation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The only effective way to raise the confidence level of a program
significantly is to give a convincing proof of its correctness. But
one should not first make the program and then prove its correctness,
because then the requirement of providing the proof would only
increase the poor programmer’s burden. On the contrary: the programmer
should let correctness proof and program grow hand in hand."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sounds like the desiderata for an interactive theorem prover. Did they
have them then?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"In this connection it might be worth-while to point out that the
purpose of abstracting is not to be vague, but to create a new
semantic level in which one can be absolutely precise."</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>"Now for the fifth argument. It has to do with the influence of the
tool we are trying to use upon our own thinking habits. … if I start
to analyse the thinking habits of myself and of my fellow human
beings, I come, [I come to the conclusion] that the tools we are
trying to use and the language or notation we are using to express or
record our thoughts, are the major factors determining what we can
think or express at all!"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This accords with my own impression. Knowing some Haskell, Common Lisp,
Python, and Lean (and probably many others) improves your thinking, but
maybe not your programs. Mine are certainly a mess.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"The analysis of the influence that programming languages have on the
thinking habits of its users, and the recognition that, by now,
brainpower is by far our scarcest resource, they together give us a
new collection of yardsticks for comparing the relative merits of
various programming languages."</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>"… tomorrow’s programming languages … to a much greater extent
than hitherto they should invite us to reflect in the structure of
what we write down all abstractions needed to cope conceptually with
the complexity of what we are designing."</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h1>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I took these from
<a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/transcriptions/EWD03xx/EWD340.html" class="uri">https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/transcriptions/EWD03xx/EWD340.html</a>
.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://brittAnderson.github.io/posts/2025-06-18-computer-languages.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Britt Anderson</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Problem of Theoretical Psychology</title>
    <link>https://brittAnderson.github.io/posts/2025-05-30-the-problem.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May 30, 2025
        
            by Britt Anderson
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Scientific psychology began as a science of the human mind: a subjective science to complement the objective sciences of physics and biology. It failed. It became satisfied with results instead of answers; measuring behaviors instead of thoughts.</p>
<p>One professional lifespan was enough to forget. Cognitive psychology again tried to model mind. It too failed. Technological progress yielded a neurobehaviorism: cognitive neuroscience; neural correlates substituted for mental causes.</p>
<p>What if the problem isn’t that the question is about minds and what a conscious person feels, but the language we use to express our ideas about answers?</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://brittAnderson.github.io/posts/2025-05-30-the-problem.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Britt Anderson</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Why</title>
    <link>https://brittAnderson.github.io/posts/2025-05-23-why.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May 23, 2025
        
            by Britt Anderson
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Why is it what it is that makes it feels like me? And: What is the what
that explains the why?</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://brittAnderson.github.io/posts/2025-05-23-why.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Britt Anderson</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>We need a new language</title>
    <link>https://brittAnderson.github.io/posts/2025-05-22-language.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <section class="header">
        Posted on May 22, 2025
        
            by Britt Anderson
        
    </section>
    <section>
        <blockquote>
<p>“I am designing a new language. I've reached the limits of
conventional languages, and now they frustrate my attempts to progress
further. They lack the power to express concepts that I need, and even
in their own domain, they're imprecise and unwieldy. They're hardly
fit for speech, let alone for thought.</p>
<p>“Existing linguistic theory is useless; I'll reevaluate basic logic to
determine the suitable atomic components for my language. This
language will support a dialect coexpressive with all of mathematics,
so that any equation I write will have a linguistic equivalent.” - Ted Chiang <a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Ted Chiang, <em>Stories of Your Life and Others</em> (Tor, 2002).<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://brittAnderson.github.io/posts/2025-05-22-language.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Britt Anderson</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
